Irene Dubicka Morawska papers 1978-1987 CPAA 93-03 CPAA 93-03
Connecticut Polish American Archives
Irene Dubicka Morawska Papers
1978-1987
CPAA 93-03
Connecticut Polish American Archives
3.0 boxes
The collection consists of material related to activities of Mrs. Irene Dubicka-Morawska within organizations that supported Solidarity after the introduction to Martial Law in Poland on December 13, 1981. Mrs. Dubicka was also active within other Polish American organizations before 1981. The bulk of the material covers the years from 1981 till 1984. The support for Solidarity was wide spread and many organizations were established not only in the US but also in Western Europe and other countries. It was a tremendous effort among Polish Americans and recent Polish immigrants to create a network of support for the Solidarity movement and for people imprisoned by the communist government of Poland. The collection consists of documentation of the establishment of such organizations, and includes correspondence, reports on political and economic situations in Poland and the program of ongoing help for political prisoners.
(2 linear ft.)
Irene Dubicka Morawska
Biographical Note
Irene Dubicka, PhD (a.k.a. Mrs. Morawska, later Mrs. Christensen) - born in -USA in 1951, a psychologist, researcher, journalist, and translator; an active member of Polish-American organizations such as (delete PAC) STUDIUM; 1981-1982 Managing and Associate Editor of New Horizon (an English-language weekend edition and offshoot of the Nowy Dziennik, a.k.a. the Polish Daily News); after Dec.1981, worked with the Committee in Support of Solidarity, N.Y.; in Feb. 1982 established Solidarity International, Inc., in New York City; Jul. 1982 - Jan. 1983 served as a co-founder with Jerzy Milewski of--and international press officer for--the Coordinating Office Abroad of NSZZ "Solidarnosc" in Brussels, Belgium; and from 1986 working as an analyst at Sandia National Laboratories in Albuquerque, New Mexico.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The collection consists of: private sociopolitical papers of Ms. Dubicka and her (now deceased) first husband Ted Morawski (IT manager/director at AIAA/IEEE/ABPI); records of Solidarity support organizations; statements pertaining to the political and economic situation in Poland after 1981 openly published by United States Government agencies and the United Nations, as well as other international human rights organizations; records related to STUDIUM (The North American Study Center for Polish Affairs), and the Polish American Congress (PAC). Memoirs of Jurek Przybylski, Solidarity activist; her masters' thesis from Columbia University on "Solidarity's Evolutionaries" (1984), and her chapter "Solidarity and Determination: Solidarity International, the Group of Delegates, and the Nationwide Resistance Committee (OKO)" (in "Poland's Solidarity Movement," eds. Lawrence Biondi and Franch Mocha; Loyola, 1984).
Arrangement
Material in the collection is divided in 3 series:
Series I - Solidarity International and other Solidarity supporting groups
Series II - Underground publications related to Solidarity and situation in Poland
Series III - Correspondence, translations.
Conditions Governing Access note
The collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Collection was donated to the archives by Irene Dubicka Morawska in 1993.
Related Material
For related material see the following collections:
Andre B. Blaszczynski Papers (CPAA 87-105)
Ewa Slusarek Papers (CPAA 93-04)
Ludmil A. Chotkowski Papers (CPAA 90-14)
Elizabeth Wasiutynski Papers (CPAA 91-03)
Clippings.; Conference of Solidarity Support Organizations.; Correspondence.; Minutes.; Position papers.; Press releases.; Solidarity International - Connecticut Chapter.; Solidarity International.; Speeches.
- Series 1. Solidarity International and other Solidarity supporting groups., 1978-1986
  - Solidarity International - declarations, program of activity, appeals, drafts, manual for chapters, by- laws, forms., 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Solidarity International - lay-outs, logo., undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Solidarity International - correspondence., 1982-1985 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Solidarity International - press releases., 1980-1982 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Solidarity International - "Wiadomosci Solidarity International" no.1 (only one published)., 1982 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Solidarity International - Addresses of parishes ready for distribution of Sweden gifts among most needing laborer families (in Poland)., circa 1982 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Solidarity International - "A Freedom Sedar" sponsored by ...Anti-Defamation League of B'naiB'rith, Polish-American Congress and ..., 1983 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Solidarity International - Board of Directors Meeting, March 5, 1983; Manual for Chapter., 1982 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Solidarity International - Press clippings., 1981-1985 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Solidarity International - fliers., 1981-1985 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Solidarity International - Connecticut Chapter: statements, application for incorporation (draft)., 1981 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Solidarity International - Polonia's effort on behalf of Polish refugees., 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Committee in Support of Solidarity - open letters (signed by Stanislaw Baranczak, Josif Brodsky, Leszek Kolakowski, Czeslaw Milosz, Susan Sontag, Thomas Wenclowa, Adam Ulam, Stanislaw Wellisz; Jakub Karpinski and Piotr Naimski; Miroslaw Chojecki), statements., 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Committee in Support of Solidarity - statements on situation in Poland., 1981-1984 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Committee in Support of Solidarity - "Report on the situation of trade unions in the Polish People's Republic" prepared by the Helsinki Committee in Poland, translated and published by ..., June., 1983 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Committee in Support of Solidarity - press releases., December 1981 - Julay 1983 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Committee in Support of Solidarity - correspondence., 1981-1983 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Committee in Support of Solidarity - repressions, list of arrested and interned., 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Committee in Support of Solidarity - "Human rights violations in the Polish People's Republic, January 1984-January 1985" A report. (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Committee in Support of Solidarity - "The lifting of martial law and human rights in Poland", a report., 1983 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Committee in Support of Solidarity - fliers., 1981-1984 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Solidarity and Human Rights Association (SHRA), speech by d. Phillips., 1983 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Conference of Solidarnosc support group (CSSO)., 1982 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Addresses of Solidarity support groups abroad., n.d. (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Support of Solidarity, Boston, statement, correspondence., 1982 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Friends of Solidarity, Washington - statements, news., 1982 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - "Solidarity with Solidarity" news, London., 1982 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Solidarity Union working Group in the United Kingdom., 1982 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Committee in Support of Solidarity, Lund, Sweden., 1982 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Comite d'Action Solidarnosc, Belgique (broadside) in French and Polish., 1982 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Comite de Defense de Solidarnosc, open letter, in French., (n.d.) (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Chrzescijanska Sluzba Wyzwolenia Narodow, Carlsberg, Germany., 1982 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - European Liaison Group and Groupe de Paris -meeting., November 1982 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Comite de Apoyo a "Solidarnosc" - Analisis de la situacion legal en Polonia despues del levantamento del estado de guerra prepared by Helsinki Committee in Poland., 1983 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - "An open letter from ISTU "Solidarnosc" to the members of the Conference on Security and Cooperation in Europe" Madrid., November 9, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - I Zjazd Koordynacyjny dzialaczy i czlonkow "Solidarnosci" w Dusseldorfie., March 13-14, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Zebrania Grupy Delegatow Krajowego Zjazdu NSZZ "Solidarnosc" za granica w Paryzu - komunikaty., 1982 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Coordinating Office Abroad of NSZZ "Solidarnosc", Brussels, declaration, statements, minutes (Nov.26;Dec.22,1982), financial records., 1982, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Coordinating Office Abroad of NSZZ "Solidarnosc" - lay-outs., 1980's (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Coordinating Office Abroad of NSZZ "Solidarnosc" - Serwis Informacyjny and Activity Reports., 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Coordinating Office Abroad of NSZZ "Solidarnosc"- press releases, appeals, 1982-1984. (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Coordinating Office Abroad of NSZZ "Solidarnosc" correspondence; including confidential letter requesting speciific electronic equipment for the Solidarity in Poland., 1982-1983, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Coordinating Office Abroad of NSZZ "Solidarnosc" - lists of arrested and interned., 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Coordinating Office Abroad of NSZZ "Solidarnosc" - analysis of situation in Poland translated and distributed., 1982-1985 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Coordinating Office Abroad of NSZZ "Solidarnosc" - Szygula, Jozef "Catastrophic accidents at the coal mines in the Polish People's Republic., 1978-1983 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Minkiewicz, Jan "Solidarity: a test-case for the eighties?"., 1982 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Visit of Solidarity Leaders (M.Wojcik,J.Milewski) in Australia., 1982 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - AFL-CIO - reading list, press releases; Free Trade Union News,No.2, and Notes, No 6, 8., 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - AFL-CIO Polish Workers Task Force - statements., (n.d.) (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - World Confederation of Labor, speech by Jan Kulakowski 1981), news, press releases., 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Kampelman remarks at CSCE meetings in Madrid., 1982 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - International Confederation of Free Trade Union - leaflet, statement, news., 1982 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Komitet Wolnych Polakow w Belgii - report by Stanislaw Kozanecki., 1979-1982 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - "Communist Control Organizations. Recent and forthcoming activities, report., 1982 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - PAEC (Polish-American Ethnic Committee) - PACH (Polish-American Communities Humanities) - "Not for Polish Americans only" project for Humanities, grant proposals, correspondence, news, notes., 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Amnesty International USA - press releases, reports., 1981-1983 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Catalog of Polish underground bulletins and publications of Solidarity support groups., 1982 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Telegram sent to ...Jaruzelski in Poland on May 22, 1985 by 33 members of the United State Senate. (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Confederation des Syndicats Chretiens de Belgique (Konfederacja Chrzescijanskich Zwiazkow Zawodowych -Sekcja Polska) - miscellaneous., (undated) (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - "Polonia Jutra" - papers by Jan Tomasz Gross, Stanislaw Kozanecki, Waclaw W.Soroka., 1978 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Polish-American Congress, miscellaneous materials., 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Pomost, miscellaneous., 1979 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Freedom House, miscellaneous., (n.d.) (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Polish Americans - varia., (n.d.) (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Press clippings and copies from serial publications related to Poland and Solidarity., 1982-1982 (Box 1, Folder 65)
- Series 2 - Underground publications related to Solidarity and situation in Poland.
  - "Apel do spoleczenstwa", KOR, Warszawa, photocopy, Ocotber 1978 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Bierezin, Jacek - "W polowie zycia", Warszawa, Niezalezna Oficyna Wydawnicza, photocopy., 1980 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - "Labour Focus on Eastern Europe", vol.4, nos 4-6 - "Poland: Solidarnosc in action" (photocopy)., 1981-1982 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Social Democrats USA - statement, press releases., 1981 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - "Who are the Workers in Polish Solidarity - and what do they want?" Commonwork Pamphlet., (1981?) (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - "Droga do wladzy", Wydzial Informacji KC PZPR., Styczen, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - "Kronika bezprawia grudzien 1981- grudzien 1982", Paris., January 1983 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Solidarnosc La Repression en Pologne Depuis 13 Decembre, 1981, Bruxelles., December 26, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - "A Conversation with Leszek Kolakowski" by George Urban. Photocopy., [1981] (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - "Poland. A Season of Light, and of Darkness" photo brochure by International Communication Agency, USA., 1982 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - The Polish Trade Union in 1984, Bogdan Lis for the Temporary Coordinating Commission., June 2, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Report to the Rockefeller Foundation and Rockefeller Brothers Fund, by the Agricultural Mission to Poland., 1982 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Poland, the lifting of martial law: an illusion of progress /The Lawyers Committee for International Human Rights; New York, N.Y.: The Committee., 1983 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Polska walka o wolnosc w dniu dzisiejszym: filozofia, satyra, rewolucja = Today's Polish fight for freedom: philosophy, satire, revolution., 1980 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - UN Commission on Human Rights - reports, press releases., 1982-1983 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Eliasz-Brantley, Ewa T. "Poland's new unions: A return to normalcy in Poland, copy from The Christian Science Monitor., 1982 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Council of Europe - "Resolution 763 on the situation on Poland"., 1982 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - US Department of Labor - "Poland - an analysis of the New Trade Union Law., October 29, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - National Academy of Sciences, Washington - "Information on Polish Scientists"., 1982 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - UN Decade for Women - "Draft declaration the Participation of Women in the Struggle for the Strengthening of International Peace... Report on the Secretary-General., 1982 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - "Srodki walki emigracji o wolna Europe Srodkowa i Wschodnia"; "O kontrofensywie emigracji w wojnie Jaruzelskiego z narodem" essays by Sigmund Lehoczky., 1983 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Letter to foreigner, by Slawomir Mrozek; Declaration by Jozef Glemp (photocopies), December 1981 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - "Poland's new unions: A return to normalcy in Poland" by E.T. Eliasz-Brantly, an article from The Christian Science Monitor, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Letter by David Day related to situation in Poland., March 1982 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Radio Free Europe - Radio Liberty, material related to its activities., 1981-1982 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Letters: Leon Boyar re: Kosciuszko Foundation; Jerzy Buczynski re: Wolna Polska., 1981 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Darnton, John "List z Warszawy"., December 16, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Przybylski, Jozef "Wspomnienia" Bruksela., 1981-1982 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Sulkowska-Bierezin, Ewa "Z obozow i ulicy";Czartek, Anna "Wiersze z Goldapi"., undated (Box 2, Folder 29)
- Series 3 - Biographical information of Irene Dubicka Morawska.
  - Biographical material related to Irene Dubicka Morawska., 1981-1982 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - "American Polonia: Solidarity and Interdependence" presentation by Irena Dubicka-Morawska at the annual convention of the American Council of Polish Cultural Clubs (ACPCC) in Chicago., July 30, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 1A)
  - Notes, remarks, speeches by Irene Dubicka Morawska, 1981-1983 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Solidarity Symposium at Loyola University, Chicago, April 23-24; paper "Solidarity and Determination", drafts, minutes, fliers, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Translations - speech and two position papers related to Solidarity by Bohdan Cywinski., 1982 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Jerzy Milewski writings translated by Irene Dubicka-Morawska., 1981-1983 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Jerzy Milewski - press clippings about him., 1982 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Material related to Solidarity Abroad - translations., 1982 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - New Horizon - materials for publication., 1980-1982 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence with Irene Dubicka-Morawska and Tadeusz Morawski., 1978-1985 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Annotated catalogs and lists of Polish books., 1980-1982 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Analysiss of political situation in Poland; list of political prisoners in Poland., 1984-1985 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - International Rescue Committee Freedom Award dinner: Lane and Irene Kirkland., 1981 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - STUDIUM The North American Study Center for Polish Affairs - status, by-laws, minutes., 1979-1985 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - "Sounds, feelings, thoughts: the poetry of Wislawa Szymborska" by Magnus J. Krynski and Robert A. Maguire (copy from Polish Review vol. XXIV., 1980 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Miscellaneous reports and underground publications related to Poland., 1981-1982 (Box 3, Folder 15)